In this video we will cover heap level 0 from exploit-exercises.com/protostar.
It’s the heap exploitation introductory challenge and is very easy.
我们再次在Ubuntu16.04LTS版本上编译它，所以基本上是一个现代系统，
see if or how it’s still exploitable.
And spoiler alert, nothing changed for this challenge, it’s super straight forward.
但我对这个视频有一个特别的想法，即使对你来说有点简单，你也可以
want to checkout what else we learn at the end.
在本系列之前的视频中，我通常会创建漏洞，然后思考一种方法
how to explain and show it to you.
但这太简单了，我想如果我把自己的解决方法记录下来会很酷的。
it, kind of like a blind solve or a speedrun.
但我没有试着超快，但它是相当直接的，我包括所有
the mistakes and pauses I made.
现在我们来看看视频，我向你解释一下我的想法
in different moments and point out some other things.
在右上角，您还可以看到一个计时器，它将跟踪多长时间
took me in real time.
But before we start doing the exploit let’s have a look at the code again.
There are two functions winner() and nowinner().
And obviously we have to somehow call winner().
We can also see there are two structs that get space allocated for them on the heap.
这里的fp构造看起来很复杂，但是你可以忽略这种奇怪，因为
when you look in the code it’s clear what it does.
We set fp to nowinner.
Notice how nowinner has no parantheses, this means it’s not being called.
This is literally the function pointer and adding paraentheses would cause a call.
And then later we have those paraentheses for fp.
And fp has been set to point to nowinner, so nowinner is executed().
我们的目标是以某种方式使用strcpy，它将溢出名称缓冲区
is only 64byte large and overwrite the function pointer.
So sounds easy.
I start by opening up the binary in gdb.
做第一次测试，但是我遇到了一个segfault，它让我吃惊了几秒钟，
but then I realized I forgot the argument parameter again.
The strcpy uses the first argument to copy into name.
Ok now we had a clean execution.
Now I want to set a good breakpoint so I disassemble main.
我在这里快速扫描汇编程序代码，主要是查看不同的函数
calls to figure out what corresponds to what in the C code.
起初我想在strcpy之前或之后设置一个断点，
抓住溢出的前后，但在最后一刻，我发现
可能不需要仔细观察，我可以直接进入魔法状态
right away.
The call rdx.
This is calling the function pointer that contains nowinner().
Ok, so I execute it again and we hit the breakpoint.
现在这个挑战是关于堆溢出的，所以我首先检查
the process with vmmap.
在这里，您可以看到哪些内存区域中有二进制代码和数据
段，我们还可以看到堆栈在哪里，以及像libc这样的共享库在哪里。
loaded too, and we also have the heap here.
So obviously I want to check out how the heap looks like.
Examine 32 64bit hex values from the start of the heap.
我立即查找我们作为参数输入的名称，它是“aaaa”，所以这里
they are.
And I also immediately look for the function pointer.
This looks like an address.
Quick sanity check with the disassemble command.
Here is a puts call using this address as a paremter, and so that is our nowinner string.
So yep, that’s nowinner.
So now we want to overwrite that with winner, so we need that address.
Here it is.
接下来，我需要弄清楚我们需要溢出多少，为了实现这一点，我只需看看
addresses to the left.
Address of the start of the name ends in 0x10, and the function pointer is ath 0x60.
So we have an offset of 0x50.
所以现在我很自信，实际上退出了gdb，希望能有个工作。
exploit right away.
So I start by writing a short python inline script to print the exploit string.
实际上，我们需要几个字符作为填充来到达函数指针和
so I print a few As.
Quick check again how many that was, 0x60-0x10 so we need 0x50.
After that we need the address of winner.
所以0x40，哎呀！
几乎犯了一个错误-这个问题有时会发生在我身上，显然我们必须开始
with 0xf6, 0x05 and then 0x40.
Because of the endianess.
现在，对于一个健全的和调试步骤，我将输出管道导入hexdump，看看它是否是
I expect.
But then I notice a 0x0a at the end, and that’s a newline.
Python print will add a newline at the end which we don’t want.
因此，现在我将脚本改为使用sys模块来直接写入
a string to stdout, so we don’t have a newline.
And I verify that again with hexdump.
And then I’m basically done and try it on the target binary.
所以输入作为参数传递，所以我使用反勾号来执行内部python命令，
and the output is then basically replaced by it and placed here as the arguments.
平地通过！
令人惊叹的！
I executed the winner function().
You see this was super simple.
所以当我用录音带上的解说词写这个剧本时，我注意到
detail that I didn’t think about.
And I actually never thought about before.
So here is the heap output again.
你看到下面的数据了吗？
That is clearly ascii.
And that’s weird, in our program we did not allocate any string like this on the heap.
这是怎么发生的？
When you look at this ascii text, then you will realize it’s in fact the printf output.
但为什么会这样？
Let’s investigate.
First I thought we could checkout valgrind.
Valgrind is an instrumentation framework for building dynamic analysis tools.
Valgrind工具可以自动检测许多内存管理和线程
bugs, and profile your programs in detail.
I really should use valgrind more often, I use it wayy to little.
But here is for example the valgrind output with tracing mallocs enabled.
And then we run our heap0 level.
我们在这里可以看到我们所做的结构的两个malloc，也可以看到malloc
didn’t do of 1024.
That’s also the only memory that is freed again.
The mallocs we do have no free.
为什么会这样？
Another interesting output is strace.
Strace traces syscalls.
虽然我们在这里看不到malloc，因为malloc只是一些算法和内存管理。
在libc中实现，我们可以看到brk syscall，它从操作系统获取内存。
in the first place.
So this is where we get memory that will then be used by libc for the heap.
所以如果malloc是libc函数，我们也可以检查ltrace，它跟踪链接的动态
library function calls.
But oddly enough we only see two mallocs for the two structs.
Nothing about the mysterious third malloc.
这可能不是很明显，但实际上已经是一个很好的提示
the mysterious malloc did not happen from a dynamically linked library call.
Which means, this malloc must have been executed for example by libc itself.
And valgrind is a bit smarter and also traces these internal mallocs.
For the third test I create a simple program that calls puts, so it prints a string.
因为我们知道堆确实包含printf输出，所以它必须对
that.
And then we can debug that program and set a breakpoint on brk.
记住，brk是当程序请求其他虚拟机时调用的系统调用
memory, and so this is called when the heap is set up.
And the heap is not always setup, only if it is required.
So if we assume printf or puts calls malloc, it would have to setup the heap first.
这也是我创建这个小测试程序的原因，因为原来的heap0
显然，打印前有规则的malloc，这让它有点烦人，所以这是
a clean example.
第二个注意事项是，当您使用BRK这样的符号名设置断点时，必须
be a symbol name for it.
And a syscall doesn’t have a symbol name.
系统调用是一个以数字作为参数来指示
syscall you want.
But there is a brk symbol, but it’s not initially found.
首先必须执行该程序才能加载动态库libc，这是
contain a brk symbol.
And infact that is a regular function as a wrapper around the brk syscall.
所以libc中的任何内容都不会直接执行syscall中断，它会调用
internal brk function.
So that;s why we can easily set a breakpoint like this.
长话短说，我们现在可以继续并点击该断点，然后检查函数
backtrace which tells us which functions have been called that lead to this brk call.
I clean that up a bit.
So here we go.
And as you can see it starts with IO_puts.
你也可以看看这些东西的libc代码，我刚刚打开了libc的镜子
on github, and you can read the code there.
为什么函数不被称为puts，但io_puts，eventhough we only use
puts when we call it, has to do with a lot of C macros in libc.
I find it really difficult to read that code.
例如，我们知道下一个函数的符号名为“IO”new“file”xsputn，但是
that doesn’t show up in the C code.
但是有一个类似的叫做io_sputn，当你往上看的时候，它会导致一个宏
that says that it’s actually IO_Xsputn.
它本身是另一个以xputn作为第一个参数的jump2宏，并且
JUMP2 is obviously another macro.
And it just keeps going like that.
Feel free to do that on your own.
But if we trust our trace we can see that at some point it calls doallocbuffer.
And there is also a comment saying: “Allocate a buffer if needed”.
So this 1024 byte malloc has to do with the standard output buffer.
printf不会立即导致syscall写入，但libc实现了很多
像这样的东西，为了获得更高的性能，通过缓冲输出而不是
waiting for files, or writing a few bigger chunks instead of a lot of small pieces.
Yeah.
I would consider this a solved mystery.
Just a little excursion into the inner workings of programs.
I hope you liked that.
See you next week.